Register of the Archives of the Soviet communist party and Soviet state microfilm collection: Russian State Archive of Contemporary History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi arkhiv noveishei istorii - RGANI)
Hoover Institution Archives
- Fond 89, Communist Party of the Soviet Union on Trial records, 1919-1992; 24 reels (Reel 1.989-1.1012)
  - Opis 31
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat (No. 198, Paragraph 5c) re relations of Soviet public organizations with socialist countries in 1980-1981, and with capitalist and liberated countries in 1980, 1980 February (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 32)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re assistance to the Afghan media, 1980 February (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 33)
    - Copy of the extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re measures in support of Olimpiada-80; list of documents sent to the TsK KPSS Politburo; list of the measures; instructions to Soviet embassies; appeal to the national Olympic committees; appeal to R. J. Kane, President of the US National Olympic Committee, and D. Miller, General Secretary; draft decree of the USSR Council of Ministers, 1980 February (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 34)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re publication of a magazine of limited circulation, Informational Bulletin of the TsK KPSS (on International Problems), 1980 March (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 35)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re a reply to a letter of P. Schroeder, US congresswoman, who offered help to children and people of Kampuchea; letter to P. Schroeder from L. Lykova, Deputy of the USSR Supreme Soviet and Chairwoman of the Commission for Work and Everyday Living Conditions of Women and for Protection of Motherhood and Childhood of the Soviet of Nationalities of the USSR Supreme Soviet, rejecting the offered help and requesting that her letter be distributed among US congressmen, 1980 March (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 36)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re a request from the leadership of the Sandinista National Liberation Front of Nicaragua (SFNL); draft decree of the USSR Council of Ministers re supply of paper and photo equipment to Nicaragua; list of photo equipment to be delivered to SFNL, 1980 March (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 37)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat approving a list of measures to strengthen the connection between the KPSS and the Sandinista National Liberation Front of Nicaragua for 1980-1981; the schedule, 1980 March (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 38)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat approving proposals presented in the memorandum of the Olimpiada-80 Organizing Committee re a meeting of the Press Commission of the International Olympic Committee in Moscow; the memorandum, 1980 March (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 39)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat authorizing a donation of $4,500 to the Pugwash Movement as the share of the Soviet Pugwash Committee to the manufacture of memorial medals in honor of the 20th anniversary of the Pugwash Movement, 1980 April (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 40)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re fulfillment of the TsK KPSS resolution On Organizational and Propaganda Measures During Preparation for the 1980 Olympic Games in Moscow, 1980 April (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 41)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat authorizing transportation to Moscow of activists from progressive organizations of Russian compatriots abroad at the expense of the Soviet Association for Cultural Relations with Compatriots Abroad, 1980 March (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 42)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat authorizing transportation and a seven-day visit to the Soviet Union for a delegation from the Youth Commission of the French Movement for Peace, 1980 April (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 43)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat authorizing appropriation of 700,000 rubles for the reconstruction of a building assigned to the Soviet Peace Committee, 1980 April (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 44)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re production and artistic assistance to the Foreign Transactions Corporation television company (US) in producing a series of documentary films about the 22nd Olympic Summer Games in Moscow, 1980 April (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 45)
    - Copy of an extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re measures to facilitate expression of public opinion against the NATO decision to manufacture and place new American missiles in Western Europe, with a list of documents sent to the Politburo of the TsK KPSS, 1980 April (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 46)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re participation of the Olimpiada-80 Organizing Committee in the meeting between the International Olympic Committee and the International Sports Federation; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from the Propaganda Department and the Department of Political Propaganda Abroad; instructions to Soviet ambassadors and Soviet of representatives, 1980 April (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 47)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re response from Soviet scientists in the field of medicine to a letter of American scientists, authors of the statement Danger: Nuclear War, 1980 April (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 48)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re inviting leaders of progressive organizations of Russian compatriots living abroad for treatment and rest in the Soviet Union in 1980; list of the leaders to be invited by the Rodina (Motherland) Association to spend vacations in the Soviet Union, 1980 April (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 49)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 50)
    - Copy of an extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re awarding orders and medals to employee of the Leningrad Carburetor-Fitting Plant of the Ministry of Automobile Industry for their exceptional success in fulfilling production tasks and in meeting additional obligations in the course of socialist competition, with a list of documents directed to the TsK KPSS Politburo, 1980 April (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 51)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re inviting A. Fenjirot(?), General Director of the Moroccan Information Agency (MIA), for a business trip to the Soviet Union, 1980 April (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 52)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re assistance to Nicaragua in eliminating illiteracy; decree of the USSR Council of Ministers, 1980 May (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 53)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re participation of Soviet representatives in the Parliament Members for Peace, Disarmament, and Security(?) international conference, 1980 May (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 54)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re assistance to the All-India Organization for Peace and Solidarity, 1980 May (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 55)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat approving instructions to Soviet ambassadors and representatives re measures to be taken to facilitate participation of national Olympic committees (NOC) in the 22nd Olympic Summer Games in Moscow; instructions to the ambassadors to Bulgaria, Hungary, North Vietnam, East Germany, Cuba, North Korea, Laos, Mongolia, Poland, Romania, and Czechoslovakia; instructions to the Soviet ambassadors to those countries whose NOC confirmed participation in the 22nd Olympic Summer Games in Moscow; instructions to the Soviet ambassadors to those countries whose NOC had not confirmed participation in the 22nd Olympic Summer Games in Moscow; instructions to the Soviet ambassador to Argentina; instructions to the Soviet ambassador to West Germany; instructions to the Soviet ambassador to Canada; instructions to the Soviet ambassador to Japan, 1980 May (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 56)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re assistance to a number of foreign delegations (up to 400 people) by offering them reduced airfare and a free stay in the International Youth Camp for the 22nd Olympic Summer Games in Moscow, 1980 June (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 57)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re participation of the Soviet sports delegation in the 22nd Olympic Summer Games in Moscow; draft decree of the USSR Council of Ministers, 1980 June (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 58)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re cooperation with Nicaragua in information and propaganda; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from the Department of Political Propaganda Abroad and the International Department, 1980 May (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 59)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re participation of the Olimpiada-80 Organizing Committee in the meeting of the Executive Committee of the International Olympic Committee; draft decree of the USSR Council of Ministers approving the members and expenses of and directives to the delegation; the directives to the Soviet delegation, 1980 June (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 60)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re a meeting of secretaries of central committees of friendly parties from socialist countries for discussion of international problems, 1980 June (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 61)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re coordination of the conference of National Commissions of the Socialist Countries for UNESCO Affairs to be held in Moscow in 1981; draft decree of the USSR Council of Ministers approving financing of the conference, the number of delegations and participants, and transportation of participants, 1980 June (Opis 31, Reel 1.1000, File 62)
  - Opis 32
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat approving a draft decree of the USSR Council of Ministers; two identical draft decrees of the USSR Council of Ministers re establishment of positions of pro-rectors for security in the Moscow and Riga institutes of civil aviation to be occupied by officers of the Committee for State Security (KGB benefits to be granted to those officers); extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from N. Savinkin, Chief of the Department of Administrative Organs; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from G. Grigorenko, Deputy Chairman of the KGB, and B. Bugaev, Minister of Civil Aviation, with attached draft decree of the USSR Council of Ministers and draft resolution of the TsK KPSS, 1979 February-April (Opis 32, Reel 1.1000, File 1)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat ordering the USSR State Bank (Gosbank) to exchange 11,600 rubles for Indian rupees; extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re a request for currency exchange from the Communist Party of India; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from R. Ulianovskii, Deputy Chief of the International Department, 1979 May (Opis 32, Reel 1.1000, File 2)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat approving a request from the African Party of Independence of Senegal (APIS) to admit S. Camara, member of the APIS Central Committee, to the Soviet Union for special training; extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from R. Ulianovskii, Deputy Chief of the International Department; memorandum (translated into Russian) to S. Cissoko, APIS Secretary General, from the Executive Secretariat of the APIS Politburo, with cover letter to B. Ponomarev from IA. Medianik, Deputy Chief of the 1st Main Directorate of the Committee for State Security (KGB), and statement from IE. Korendiasov, Reference Assistant of the International Department, re confirmation of the request by S. Cissoko, 1979 May (Opis 32, Reel 1.1000, File 3)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re a statement to be delivered to the first secretaries of the TsK KPSS of the union republics and KPSS committees in krais and oblasts; the statement re increase in price of gold and silver jewelry, furs, rugs, cars, and imported furniture sets; one page from a distribution list; note to the General Department from B. Gostev with the list of officials to whom the statement should be sent; extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat; additional statement, accompanied by the cover letter to the TsK KPSS from B. Gostev, Chief of the Department of Planning and Financial Organs, 1979 June (Opis 32, Reel 1.1000, File 4)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat approving the request from the Communist Party of Israel (CPI) to admit D. Vilner, member of the CPI, to the Soviet Union for special training in party security; extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from K. Brutents, Deputy Chief of the International Department; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from M. Vilner, 1979 June (Opis 32, Reel 1.1000, File 5)
    - Resolution of the Secretariat of the TsK KPSS approving a request from the Lebanese Communist Party (LCP) to admit ten party activists to the Soviet Union for special training in party security; two identical ciphered letters to an unidentified addressee in Beirut to be passed on to G. Hawi, Secretary General of the LCP; extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from K. Brutents, Deputy Chief of the International Department, 1979 June-July (Opis 32, Reel 1.1000, File 6)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 32, Reel 1.1000, File 7)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat approving a request from the Lebanese Communist Party (LCP) to supply a mobile radio station to the leadership of the LCP; extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from K. Brutents, Deputy Chief of the International Department, 1979 July (Opis 32, Reel 1.1000, File 8)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat approving a request from C. Almeyda, Secretary General of the Socialist Party of Chile, to admit ten party activists to the Soviet Union for military training; extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Zagladin, Deputy Chief of the International Department; memorandum (translated into Russian) to the TsK KPSS from C. Almeyda, 1979 June-August (Opis 32, Reel 1.1000, File 9)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat ordering that the Committee for State Security (KGB) and the General Staff of the Soviet Armed Forces consider the possibility of delivering non-Soviet weapons to the People's Party of Iran (PPI); extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Zagladin, Deputy Chief of the International Department; memorandum (translated into Russian) to the TsK KPSS from N. Kianuri, Secretary General of the Central Committee of the PPI; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from IU. Andropov and B. Ponomarev, 1979 August; 1980 July (Opis 32, Reel 1.1000, File 10)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re establishment of relations with a new revolutionary organization in Thailand in order to consolidate the Thai People's Revolutionary Movement (in cooperation with friends from North Vietnam and Laos) on the basis of Marxism and Leninism; two identical directives to the Soviet ambassadors to North Vietnam and Laos; extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Zagladin, Deputy Chief of the International Department; memorandum (translated into Russian) to the TsK KPSS from Bunyen Worthong [representative of the leadership of the Thai People's Revolutionary Movement], 1979 August-October (Opis 32, Reel 1.1000, File 11)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat assigning the responsibility for welcoming G. Cervetti, member of the leadership of the Italian Communist Party, to B. Ponomarev and V. Zagladin; extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Zagladin, Deputy Chief of the International Department, 1979 October (Opis 32, Reel 1.1000, File 12)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re measures to oppose the policy of the Vatican toward socialist countries; two identical memoranda to the TsK KPSS from M. Zimianin, L. Zamiatin, E. Tiazhelnikov,V. Zagladin, O. Rakhmanin, V. Chebrikov, I. Zemskov, and V. Kuroedov; one page from the list of officials to whom the excerpts from the resolution should be sent; distribution list of party, governmental, and social organizations; extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat, without items 4 and 5 of the agenda; extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat with items 4 and 5 of the agenda; cover letter to the TsK KPSS from M. Zimianin, L. Zamiatin, E. Tiazhelnikov, V. Zagladin, O. Rakhmanin, V. Chebrikov, I. Zemskov, and V. Kuroedov presenting the updated memorandum and draft resolution of the TsK KPSS; the draft resolution, with handwritten comments and amendments; cover letter to the Department of International Information from G. Tsinev, Deputy Chairman of the Committee for State Security (KGB), presenting a memorandum re the position of Poland with respect to the policy and strategy of the Vatican; the memorandum signed by the Deputy Chief of the 1st Main Directorate of the Committee for State Security (KGB); statement to the TsK KPSS from V. Ignatenko, Deputy Chief of the Department of Political Propaganda Abroad, re utilization of the material submitted by the KGB while preparing the draft resolution of the TsK KPSS; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from E. Tiazhelnikov, Chief of the Propaganda Department, L. Zamiatin, Chief of the Department of Political Propaganda Abroad, and A. Cherniaev, Deputy Chief of the International Department, presenting their comments to the Tsinev memorandum; two brief handwritten notes; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Kuroedov, Chairman of the Council for Religious Affairs under the USSR Council of Ministers, presenting an analytical report on current social, political, and ideological activities of the Vatican, with proposals; the analytical report; resolution of the Secretariat of the TsK KPSS approving the analytical report, 1979 September; 1979 November; 1980 February; 1980 July; 1980 September (Opis 32, Reel 1.1000, File 13)
    - Resolution of the Secretariat of the TsK KPSS re awarding an order and medals to citizens of the German Democratic Republic; copy of an extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat, 1979 November (Opis 32, Reel 1.1000, File 14)
    - Draft resolution of the TsK KPSS approving the Regulations on the Mobilization Activity of Central Committees of Union Republics, and KPSS Committees in Krais, Oblasts, and Raions and approving the measures to be taken to improve the preparedness of KPSS committees for mobilization; the draft regulations; one page of the list of party officials and KPSS committees the regulations were sent to; list of KPSS committees, with the number of copies to be delivered to each of the committees; extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat approving the regulations; the regulations; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from N. Savinkin, Chief of the Department of Administrative Organs, G. Pavlov, Administrator of the Administration of TsK KPSS Affairs, N. Petrovichev, Deputy Chief of the Department of Organizational and Party Work, and K. Bogoliubov, Deputy Chief of the General Department, re approval of the regulations; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from N. Savinkin, N. Petrovichev, and K. Bogoliubov on instructional conferences to be held re mobilization activity of KPSS committees, 1979 November; 1980 May (Opis 32, Reel 1.1000, File 15)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 32, Reel 1.1000, File 16)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat approving a draft decree of the USSR Council of Ministers re increase in personnel of the KGB office of the Ministry of Public Security of Mongolia; three draft decrees of the USSR Council of Ministers (differently formatted); extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from N. Savinkin, Chief of the Department of Administrative Organs; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from IU. Andropov, Chairman of the KGB; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS, 1979 December - 1980 January (Opis 32, Reel 1.1000, File 17)
    - Draft resolution of the TsK KPSS on selection of party, Soviet, and VLKSM officials for leading positions in the Committee for State Security (KGB); two similar memoranda to the TsK KPSS from IU. Andropov, Chairman of the KGB; two identical draft decrees of the USSR Council of Ministers (differently formatted); two identical lists presenting the number of officials to be selected for a two-year educational course (in the KGB School) for leading KGB personnel from various geographical areas; extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat, 1980 January (Opis 32, Reel 1.1000, File 18)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat approving a request from the Communist Party of Chile (CPC) to admit twenty party activists to the Soviet Union in 1980 and eight representatives of the CPC leadership in 1980-1981 for training in clandestine work; extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Shaposhnikov, Deputy Chief of the International Department; memorandum (translated into Russian) to the TsK KPSS from L. Corvalán, Secretary General of the CPC, 1979 November - 1980 January (Opis 32, Reel 1.1000, File 19)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat approving a draft decree of the USSR Council of Ministers re technical support to be given to Afghanistan to build a 1,000 KW broadcasting radio station; three draft decrees of the USSR Council of Ministers (differently formatted); extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat; brief statement from K. Simonov, Chief of the Department of Transport and Communications, confirming the decision of the Afghan government to build a radio station; brief handwritten note; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from K. Simonov and R. Ulianovskii, Deputy Chief of the International Department; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from S. Skachkov [GKES - State Commission for Economic Cooperation] and N. Talyzin, Minister of Communications; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS; draft decree of the USSR Council of Ministers, 1979 December - 1980 January (Opis 32, Reel 1.1000, File 20)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re postponement of the beginning of Soviet broadcasts to the United States from Cuban territory; two similar memoranda to the TsK KPSS from L. Zamiatin, Chief of the Department of Political Propaganda Abroad, and K. Simonov, Chief of the Department of Transport and Communications; extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from N. Talyzin, Minister of Communications and S. Lapin, 1980 January-February (Opis 32, Reel 1.1000, File 21)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat authorizing the prolongation of the visit of I. Nazish, Secretary General of the Communist Party of Pakistan, for two more months in order to provide him with training in clandestine work; extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from R. Ulianovskii, Deputy Chief of the International Department, 1980 February (Opis 32, Reel 1.1000, File 22)